in our last session when we looked at
Aristotle's notion of substance I talked
about his distinction between form and
matter
the distinction that corresponds to the
difference between being and becoming
between actuality and potentiality
but then when we look at the Zenith of
his thinking we see him
speaking of his concept of God which is
that of pure form or of absolute
actuality that which has being but no
becoming
actuality without potentiality
and popularly his definition of God is
defined as the UN
moved
mover
or the uncaused cause
the formal first cause of everything
else that exists in the world
now remember when he had his idea of
each entity being made up every
substance being made up of form and
matter except for the pure form that it
is the form within something that
controls the development of that thing's
potential
that's the form within the eight Acorn
that moves the acorn to become an oak
tree we've already established that
and so we now are left with the question
well if you have all these individual
entities running about with their
independent forms and matters
how does it all fit together and we're
right back to the question the thales
was asking originally of the one and the
many
of unity and diversity
so over all the individual substances
that we encounter in the real world
there stands Aristotle's God
who is pure form
he has Eternal being
and he also must have the power
to organize and generate and move
everything else that moves remember the
ancient Greeks were looking for the
answer to being and to the answer of
motion
and so he said that the ultimate source
of all motion
is pure form this absolute form directs
the individual forms that are moving in
this world
now
how does he do it
or for Aristotle the pure form is
himself
not moving or itself not moving
yet it is the Mover
how does it move
other things well it moves everything
all the other forms by attraction and
the analogy is the moth and the flame
the flame stays in the same place but it
moves the moth by attracting The Moth
it's almost like a primitive sense of
magnetism or of gravity if you will
now again Aristotle's God is not a
personal uh God like judeo-christianity
has he is this uh or it is this ultimate
pure being of force and Power
from which everything else comes and of
course this being is eternal
and exists by necessity as I said ideas
have consequences the greatness of
Augustine who is considered the greatest
Theologian of the first Millennium of
Christianity was that he was able to
create a kind of synthesis between
biblical Christianity and platonic
philosophy likewise and this is a bit of
an oversimplification in my opinion but
nevertheless it's the standard rap that
the greatness of Aquinas Thomas Aquinas
was his ability to create a synthesis
between
Christianity and Aristotelian philosophy
now as I said that's oversimplified
because there were many elements of
Aristotle's philosophy particularly with
respect to his understanding of the
relationship between God and the world
that Aquinas
comprehensively rejected but we'll wait
until we get to Aquinas before we see
that but for now we have the rudimentary
concepts of an eternal self-existing
being that must be for anything else to
exist
a necessary being as it were
but there is no concept of conscious
personal
Divine Providence
or of a voluntary creation
in Aristotle's view of God
he's his view of God will Durant
referred to Aristotle's God as being
somewhat similar to the king of England
He reigns but he doesn't rule he's more
or less a figurehead there that's a
philosophical necessity to explain the
things that are
now since we've seen already the
significant difference between Aristotle
and Plato with respect to their
metaphysics their doctrines of being in
becoming
that also falls over into the realm of
epistemology where Aristotle also
differed sharply from his mentor with
respect to the idea of how we know what
we know remember Plato had his theory of
recollection where the ideas are
embedded in The Souls of all people and
it's just a matter of getting that
knowledge out that's already there so
that knowledge is if you remember the
technical term off priori
for Aristotle knowledge is a posteriori
that is it comes from experience
it comes initially through sense
perception
a sense perception is an impression that
we have through one of the five senses
an experience of seeing or hearing or
tasting or touching or smelling those
are the senses and we perceive things
through those five senses and from sense
perception comes an image in the brain
or in the mind
you see something and you have an image
of what you see in the mind and then out
of these images come ideas
so that knowledge or ideas are dependent
not upon recalling information you're
born with but from learning things
through this process of using the senses
with the mind working with the senses
now the Mind does have a priori
abilities
no knowledge but abilities the mind is
that organ in the body or in the human
person that has the ability to work with
the raw data of Sensation that we have
to synthesize to synthesize these
Impressions to abstract them to combine
them put them together and form
intelligible ideas
now at this point I'm going to give you
another distinction
and that is this distinction
that we make in philosophy between
realism
and nominalism
now if you recall when we looked at
Plato I confused everybody when I said
Plato is at the same time a realist and
an idealist
using those terms in this way that for
Plato the ideas that we have the ideas
of humanness chairness and so on that
those ideas
are real entities
and hence he is called a realist
for Aristotle
ideas are not
real
in the sense of having being within them
and so the old debate that goes on
through the Middle Ages and even today
that is called the argument of a realism
and nominalism goes back to this dispute
between Plato and his disciple Aristotle
and it goes back to two words not in
Greek but in Latin
where we have the word race
in Latin and every attorney or judge
knows what that means
a race in legal terms is the thing
that's that's the matter thing a race is
simply the word for thing
and the word nomina
nomina
in Latin means
name
we say that some people are nominal
Christians we mean by that they are
and Christians in name only we talk
about denominations or nominating you
name somebody for a particular office in
an election that's a nomination putting
their name up for election and so the
word nomina means name nominalism means
simply
that universals
universals
which in this case are
generic ideas tree Ness elephant-ness
humanness all these ideas that we have
that we universalize
for
Aristotle
are not things
but they're names
I had a chair up here when I talked
about Plato and I said how do you
recognize that this chair is a chair
and how can we call so many different uh
entities by the same name chair
well for Plato Plato says well in the
Eternal world there's this pure chernus
this pure idea of chareness and when we
see a close approximation of it an
imperfect copy of it in the material
world we say aha I'm getting a
recollection of that idea of chair Ness
and so I identify this object as a chair
Aristotle says no he says that's not how
it works he said we we start to learn
and we perceive an object in our mommy
we say what's that and you say well
that's a chair and then you see another
object and your mother tells you that's
a chair too even though it differs
significantly from the first chair that
your mind has the ability to have all
these Sensations and all these images
and to put them together an abstract
combine and relate these experience and
come up with a generic concept of
chair-ness
doesn't mean there really is such a
thing as chairness there's just this
Universal idea that is a construction of
the Mind
it's a name and that's all it is is a
name
that we assign to Universal General
categories
and we use that when we apply
particulars into those various uh a
different spheres and so we would say
that Aristotle was not a realist in the
sense of believing that Universal ideas
had independent reality but he was a
nominalist in this so far as he believed
that Universal concepts are merely
mental
names
that we have conceived by the mind
he also taught that truth
involves
conformity
between the mind
and a thing this is an early form of the
correspondence theory of Truth what he
meant by that is when
your mental idea
corresponds to the external object that
you are seeking to know
or conforms to it
when your idea of chair of the
particular chair that you see
corresponds to the reality of that chair
you have truth
when your idea does not conform to that
actual object you have error or you have
falsehood and so part of the whole
process of learning is to constantly
seek more precision and exactitude in
conforming our ideas or concepts of
things to actual entities that exist out
there
now
in all of this
Aristotle
thought that at the beginning of
knowledge
there have to be certain rules that we
follow
for science to take place
and he distinguished among all these
different disciplines of investig
investigative inquiry as I said physics
biology astronomy ethics
jurisprudence and Aesthetics and all the
rest
he said but there are certain principles
of knowing
that have to be applied to all fields of
inquiry
for science to be possible
and so he talked about the role of logic
in The Knowing process
now it's important that Aristotle did
not consider the study of logic a
separate independent science from all of
the other sciences that he was engaged
in
but rather he called logic
the organon
of all science
now the word organon simply means
instrument
just like musicians have instruments
that they need to use to play music
and the sculptor has an instrument
namely the Chisel or the hammer that he
needs to have to make his statue
so the instrument that we need in order
to construct real knowledge is logic
and he sees logic as a necessary
instrument for all intelligible
discourse
I'm going to explain that in a second
but first it's important particularly in
light of the age in which we live which
is one of the most anti-rational periods
in the history of Western thought
where people are not only accepting
contradictions and irrationality they're
glorying in it
and we've seen the break up of rational
coherent thought remember Francis
Schaefer's little book Escape from
reason
existentialism has launched a massive
assault against the rational and so on
and we've seen in our own day the
theater of the Absurd and John Cage's
arbitrary forms of music and so on
Aristotle did not invent logic
let me say it again Aristotle did not
invent logic anymore than Christopher
Columbus
invented America
what Aristotle sought to do was to
articulate
how logical categories function
he didn't think that he was the first
logical person
he didn't think that logic didn't exist
before him
he's simply asking the question as a
philosopher what has to be for us to be
able to speak intelligibly
about biology or astronomy or physics or
anything else
and he said well there are certain basic
needs that have to be met for
intelligibility to occur and one is that
our statements
be logically
constructed what he means by that is
that they not violate the first law of
logic which is the law of
non-contradiction
before I go into that let me just give
one other distinction he makes in terms
of his exposition of how logic Works he
says that logic and all science depend
upon
the relationships
between the general
and the particular
or what we would say between the subject
and the predicate
if I'm a biologist and I want to know
what a an amoeba is I may say an amoeba
in order to distinguish it from a frog I
will say an amoeba is
something
I will predicate
characteristics
I will mention the particulars that
Define
a an amoeba
and then contrast it or compare it with
the particulars that Define a fraud
now when you were in junior high school
or in grade school you learned about the
whole process of classification
where you have the genus and the species
the kingdom and the phylas and so on
and we say well you know there's the
animal kingdom
and the plant kingdom
now they're both
examples of living things
but they're two completely different
kingdoms
they have one thing in common there's
the general
they're both bios they're both alive
okay
but then we talk about different kinds
of life to distinguish between animals
and
vegetables or
plants
now indefinite defining things you pay
attention both to similarities and
differences
we are all in the animal kingdom
but we're not baboons
we further differentiate and
particularize within the animal kingdom
the difference between human beings and
baboons and then we go into further
Precision when we talk about male and
female
and we further particularize by making
additional predications about
individuals where this man has a name he
has an age he has a certain height and
weight and so on where we get more and
more and more precise
but that's what's necessary for
knowledge to take place and for language
to work you need both the general and
the particular you need the subject and
the predicate and they cannot
be brought in irreconcilable opposition
to each other
so therefore he postulates the law of
non-contradiction
which says that a cannot be a and non-a
at the same time and in the same
relationship which in simple terms means
that this piece of chalk
cannot be a piece of chalk and a
kangaroo
at the same time
in the same way
now I can be a father
and a son
and a brother
all at the same time we may predicate
three distinct things about me at the
same time but
not in the same relationship
I cannot be a son to my father and have
him be
my son
at the same time and in the same
relationship
something cannot be what it is and not
be what it is at the same time in the
same relationship
now there can be nothing simpler or more
foundational
to human intelligibility than that and
yet in our day we've seen wholesale and
widespread rejection of the most
foundational principle that Aristotle
defined for Science and it's not only
fatal to theology it's fatal to science
because it removes the necessary
instrument
for understanding now there are many
other contributions that Aristotle has
given to the history of philosophy again
as I said some have said that the whole
history of theoretical thought is only a
footnote to Plato and Aristotle but
since this is an overview we're going to
have to leave those other matters for
your further research